<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0"><channel><title><![CDATA[Ashish's Blog RSS Feed]]></title><description><![CDATA[Ashish Selvaraj's ruminations about software & life.]]></description><link>https://ashishselvaraj.com</link><generator>GatsbyJS</generator><lastBuildDate>Sat, 18 Feb 2023 07:06:18 GMT</lastBuildDate><item><title><![CDATA[Not Evil Sudoku]]></title><description><![CDATA[Not Evil Sudoku is a clean, minimalist sudoku app on the App Store. Background In February of 2022, I got the urge to play sudoku and as…]]></description><link>https://ashishselvaraj.com/notevilsudoku/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://ashishselvaraj.com/notevilsudoku/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 18 Feb 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;Not Evil Sudoku is a clean, minimalist sudoku app on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://appstoreconnect.apple.com/apps/1614071642/appstore&quot;&gt;App Store&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Background&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In February of 2022, I got the urge to play sudoku and as most people would, I simply searched &lt;em&gt;sudoku&lt;/em&gt; on the App Store.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To my dismay, I found that most of the top sudoku apps were riddled with ads and had horrible UX. At the time I was learning SwiftUI to build another app and I reasoned that this would be a nice project to get my feet wet. Little did I know that it would take off and I would spend hours and hours working on it. I&apos;ve worked on it in some capacity over almost every weekend since April 14th when it launched!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I named it Not Evil because it was meant to be free from the spam and cheap monetization hacks that other apps used. Some sudoku apps even showed video ads in-between moves!!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Looking back this project had clear product-market fit. The App Store had few clean, well-built sudoku apps and Not Evil Sudoku filled that niche perfectly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Advertisements&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To be clear, I&apos;m not against ads at all. Ads allow everyone no matter their economic background to experience and enjoy the internet. Subscriptions are great but it&apos;s hard to deny that they present a significant barrier for those without disposable income or even those from poorer countries (especially since many companies don&apos;t have parity pricing).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;User Experience&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My goal was to have a sudoku solving experience that was as joyful as possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;Sticking to Apple&apos;s Design Language&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was relatively easy with SwiftUI and at the time I wasn&apos;t great at design so it was the right choice.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref-1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn-1&quot; class=&quot;footnote-ref&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It also made the app feel more at home on the user&apos;s screen and made it a lot cleaner and easier to navigate. If Apple designed a sudoku app, I like to think it would look a lot like Not Evil Sudoku.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;Avoiding Information Overload&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A lot of sudoku apps tout their customization capabilities but I found that trying to find the feature you wanted was enormously difficult. They were usually just all added to a very long list with inscrutable names. It seemed like they&apos;d added every feature a user had ever requested and done so in a very sloppy and overwhelming way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wanted Not Evil Sudoku to be customizable but without being overwhelming. Users can switch between light/dark mode, have custom app icons and change themes. Along with this, every game feature is explained in a footnote underneath its toggle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Monetization&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Monetization is one of the hardest parts of building anything but particularly if your product has &quot;Not Evil&quot; in its name. I just knew that I would get snarky comments (and I wasn&apos;t wrong).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wanted to give users value even if they didn&apos;t pay a dime while also ensuring that the app was sustainable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since the app was focused solely on improving the user experience of sudoku, ads were out of the question. Subscriptions also didn&apos;t seem like a good fit. Maybe some kind of subscription for power users would be a good addition to the app in the future but it certainly wouldn&apos;t make sense for a casual sudoku player.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I ended up going with giving users a free sudoku puzzle every day and having a one-time in-app purchase that unlocked unlimited games, charts and other perks. Overall, this strategy has worked out pretty well, although I still get the occasional &quot;OMG YOU HAVE IN APP PURCHASES THATS SO IRONIC AND EVIL&quot; comment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Initally, I had two options:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Plus - Unlimited Games&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pro - Unlimited Games, Charts, Custom App Icons&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But they differed in cost by only $2 and Pro&apos;s feature list kept getting longer and longer. At some point Plus just stopped making sense. To be honest, I don&apos;t think it ever made sense. I added it initially because I feared that people might complain about unlimited games not being free and wanted to give them a cheap way to unlock it. But, those people were going to complain anyway, no matter the price.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Product decisions based on fear are always going to be poor product decisions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Mental Health&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whenever YouTubers would talk about dealing with hate comments, some part of me wondered why they took random comments on the internet seriously. I felt bad for them but at I never understood it. That is until I published Not Evil Sudoku.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think to truly understand, you need to create something and put it out there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Someone ripping you or your work apart hurts even if they are a faceless stranger on the world wide web.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most people on Twitter were very supportive even in the beginning when it was miles behind other sudoku apps &lt;sup id=&quot;fnref-2&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn-2&quot; class=&quot;footnote-ref&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I posted it on Reddit, I braced for impact and the anxiety of posting your work for others to comment on and judge is really something else. I got the classic &quot;how can it be not evil when it has purchases&quot; but otherwise people were very kind.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most stress came from those 1-star review notifications from App Store Connect. Nowadays, I don&apos;t even flinch but in the beginning, it affected me quite a bit. I remember being unable to focus or think straight in a graph theory lecture because someone&apos;s comment was bouncing around in my head.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Takeaways&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, if you build anything, remember this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You aren&apos;t responsible for making everyone happy. As long as your product does everything you claim it does, you don&apos;t need to feel guilty. If they don&apos;t like it, they can leave, it&apos;s not your duty to satisfy their every whim.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If your product doesn&apos;t deliver value, people won&apos;t pay for it. Stop worrying about the price. You don&apos;t need to correct for that yourself. I was so insecure about the product that I made it unsustainably cheap. Price based on what you feel is right and you can always change course if the market proves you wrong.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&quot;fn-1&quot;&gt;I&apos;d like to think that I&apos;m much better now!&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref-1&quot; class=&quot;footnote-backref&quot;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&quot;fn-2&quot;&gt;It isn&apos;t anymore!&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref-2&quot; class=&quot;footnote-backref&quot;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[New Beginnings]]></title><description><![CDATA[In my previous website my blog posts were simply JSON objects and a simple forEach would loop through and display them somewhat nicely. Stop…]]></description><link>https://ashishselvaraj.com/new-beginnings/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://ashishselvaraj.com/new-beginnings/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 17 Feb 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;In my previous website my blog posts were simply JSON objects and a simple forEach would loop through and display them somewhat nicely. Stop judging me, we all have to start somewhere!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But formatting posts was impossible and I&apos;d been waiting for some free time so that I could pursue a less hacky solution. Despite programming for a somewhat long time (since I was 12!), I was aware of static site generation only peripherally.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I discovered Jekyll last year through &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/emilbaehr/automatic-app-landing-page&quot;&gt;Emil Baehr&apos;s Automatic App Landing Page&lt;/a&gt;. I found that template the day of Not Evil Sudoku&apos;s launch and had only a few hours before I was due to board an international flight. &lt;sup id=&quot;fnref-1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn-1&quot; class=&quot;footnote-ref&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Needless to say, I butchered it as I raced to get something decent running and definitely didn&apos;t appreciate how cool Jekyll (and static site generation as a a whole) was.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Originally, this website was meant to be built with Jekyll but since Gatsby uses React, it would let me re-use some of the components from my previous personal website (May 2021) which seemed neat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Being able to write posts in &lt;em&gt;Markdown&lt;/em&gt; {is an} &lt;strong&gt;incredible&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;level-up&lt;/code&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&quot;fn-1&quot;&gt;Why did I plan to launch the same day as travelling internationally? Shhh, I&apos;m a busy guy.&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref-1&quot; class=&quot;footnote-backref&quot;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content:encoded></item></channel></rss>